Guide to the Phillip Lopate Papers YCAL MSS 1083
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Phillip Lopate papers
circa 1951-2015
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lopate, Phillip, 1943-
YCAL MSS 1083
43.5 Linear Feet (83 boxes)
The Phillip Lopate papers consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, teaching files, printed materials, and audiovisual and computer media documenting Lopate's career as a writer, critic, and university instructor. Materials date from circa 1951 to 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 82 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 83 (audiovisual media): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Phillip Lopate and James S. Jaffe Rare Books LLC on the Sinclair Lewis Fund and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: I. Correspondence, circa 1958-2006 and undated. II. Writings, 1963-2009 and undated. III. Personal Papers, 1951-2000. IV. Teaching Materials, 1968-1975. V. Printed Materials, 1963-2015 and undated. VI. Computer and Audiovisual Media, 1934-2015 and undated.
Phillip Lopate (1943-)
Born in Brooklyn, New York in 1943, Phillip Lopate is the author of works of fiction, poetry, personal and literary essays, and film criticism. He is also the editor of several anthologies. Lopate received a B.A. from Columbia College of Columbia University in New York City in 1964 and his Ph.D. in English Education from Union Graduate School, in Cincinnati, Ohio in 1979. He has received various fellowships, including a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1988, and was inducted into the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 2006. Lopate began his career as Project Director of the Teachers and Writers Collaborative in Manhattan, providing instruction to elementary school children in poetry and fiction writing, among other topics. After twelve years, he transitioned into higher education, holding teaching positions and professorships at institutions such as Hofstra University, Fordham University, New York University, and the University of Houston. He currently teaches nonfiction writing at Columbia's School of the Arts. Lopate's notable works include his memoir, Being With Children (1975), his essay collections Bachelorhood (1981), Getting Personal (2003), and The Rug Merchant (1987), a work of fiction.
Scope and Contents
The Phillip Lopate papers consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, teaching files, printed materials, and audiovisual and computer media, dating from circa 1951 to 2015. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence with editors and publishers, notes, manuscripts, drafts, typescripts, proofs, and related materials that document his work as an essayist, literary critic, and author of short stories, poetry, biographies, and screenplays. Personal papers contain Lopate's personal diaries and journals, memo books, and notebooks, as well as interviews and news clippings about Lopate. Teaching files include Lopate's correspondence with other educators, student course evaluations, teaching diaries, and comics drawn by students at Public School 75 in Manhattan, New York. Printed materials contain publications authored or edited by Phillip Lopate, publications which feature his writing, and special edition publications. Computer and audiovisual media include interviews, lectures, and audio recordings on computer disks, optical media, audiocassettes, videocassettes, and film.
TypeCollection
https://preservica.library.yale.edu/explorer/explorer.html#prop:4&b6e88446-c565-4912-be6f-414a09ff51b7
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 21st century -- Archives; American literature -- 20th Century; American literature -- 21st century; American literature -- Study and teaching; Composition (Language arts) -- Study and teaching; English literature -- Study and teaching; Burckhardt, Rudy; Glück, Louise, 1943-; Padgett, Ron, 1942-; Shapiro, David, 1947-; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Lopate, Phillip, 1943-; Trilling, Diana, 1905-1996; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975; Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956; Ozick, Cynthia
- Correspondence, circa 1958-circa 2015 and undated; 1; 10.5 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into ten subseries: Letters from family, Letters regarding film, Letters by [Phillip Lopate], Emails, mostly from friends, alphabetized, Lily Lopate (daughter/writer) correspondence and emails, Letters from old friends and frequent correspondents, Letters from the famous and near-famous, Older correspondence, Public appearances, translations, and business correspondence, and Reviews, publicity, and letters for books
  Scope and Contents
  This series primarily consists of Phillip Lopate's correspondence with family, friends, writers, and critics such as Ron Padgett, David Shapiro, Rudy Burckhardt, Johnathan Cott, Sidney Tillim, Aaron Fogel, and Louise Glück. Other notable correspondents are Max Apple, Terry Caesar, Diana and Lionel Trilling, and Laura Furman. Included is an extensive amount of email correspondence with Lopate's daughter, author Lily Lopate, and correspondence with his mother Frances Lopate and brother Leonard. The series also contains correspondence related to Lopate's public appearances, such as lectures, speaking engagements, and interviews, as well as correspondence with publishers and agents.
  The arrangement follows Lopate's original organization of his correspondence, and subseries and folder titles are based on the description he provided.
  - Letters from family
    - Ascher, Carol, circa 1964-circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Lopate, Betty Ann, circa 1965-circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
    - Lopate, Frances, circa 1965-circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lopate, Frances, circa 1965-circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Lopate, Frances, given to Phillip upon her death, circa 1968-circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lopate, Joan, circa 1969-circa 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lopate, Leonard, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters regarding film
    - Letters regarding film, circa 2001-circa 2013 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Letters by [Phillip Lopate]
    - Letters of recommendation [by Phillip Lopate], circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Letters to others, circa 1970-circa 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - Letters to others, printouts, circa 2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letters to Alan Feldman, circa 1965-circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - [Lopate] Betty Ann, letters to, circa 1975-circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Emails, mostly from friends, alphabetized [printouts]
    - "A" General, 2006–2015 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Anderson, Laurie, 2010–2015 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Apple, Max, 2010–2015 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "B" General, 2006–2014 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Baumbach, Jonathan, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Beattie, Ann, 2008–2015 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Beller, Thomas, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Boullosa, Carmen, 2006–2015 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Boyers, Robert, 2011–2015 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "C" General, 2006–2015 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Coleman, Kate, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "D" General, 2007–2015 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "E" General, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "F" General, 2008–2010 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Frank, Edwin, 2011–2015 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Freed, Lynn, 2006–2015 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "G" General, 2007–2015 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Galchen, Rivka, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "H" General, 2011–2015 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Hampl, Patricia, 2007–2013 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Hask, Molly, 2005–2014 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Hoffman, Adina, 2013–2014 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Huxtable, Ada Louise, 2006–2008 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "I" General, 2010–2013 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "J" General, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "K" General, 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Kiernan, Fran, 2010–2013 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Kincaid, Jamaica, 2008–2013 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "L" General, 2004–2015 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Lethem, Jonathan, 2005–2015 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "M" General, 2007–2015 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Morris, Paul, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "N" General, 2014–2015 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - "O" General, 2008–2015 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - "P" General, 2005–2013 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - "Q" General, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - "R" General, 2006–2013 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - "S" General, 2005–2015 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Seshadri, Vijay, 2007–2015 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Shapiro, David, 2001–2014 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Shields, David, 2007–2013 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - "T" General, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Taylor, Ben, 2009–2015 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - "V" General, 2010–2012 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - "W" General, 2009–2015 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - "Z" General, 2005–2013 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Lily Lopate (daughter/writer) correspondence and emails [printouts]
    - Lopate, Lily, 2007–2015 (Box 4, Folder 69-73)
    - Lopate, Lily, 2007–2015 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Letters from old friends and frequent correspondents
    - Arnstein, Flora, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Bingham, Sallie, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Birkerts, Sven, circa 1994-circa 1996 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Brickner, Richard, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Burckhardt, Rudy, circa 1985-circa 1988 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Cole, Peter, undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Cott, Jonathan, undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - DeLynn, Jane, undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Dintenfrass, Mark, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Elman, Richard, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Feldman, Alan, circa 1965-circa 1977 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Fogel, Aaron, undated (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Gornick, Vivian, circa 1986-circa 1996 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Hearon, Shelby, circa 1978-circa 2010 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Hoffman, Adina, circa 1987-circa 1996 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Hadas, Rachel, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Kaminsky, Marc, undated (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Lauthbach, Ann, circa 1980-circa 1986 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Lazar, David, circa 1993-circa 1994 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Lowry, Beverly, circa 1994-circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Luddy, Tom, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Nye, Naomi Shihab, circa 1987-circa 1994 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Masters, Hilary, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Tillim, Sidney, circa 1983-circa 1996 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Zavatsky, Bill, circa 1980-circa 1982 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Letters from the famous and near-famous
    Consists of correspondence with other writers and people Lopate considered "well-known," such as Max Apple, Diana and Lionel Trilling, and Cynthia Ozick, and those whom he considered "moderately-known," including Terry Caesar and Laura Furman.
    - Letters from other writers, general, circa 1990-circa 2010 (Box 7, Folder 100-101)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "A" General, undated (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "B" General, circa 1974-circa 2007 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "C" General, circa 1992-circa 1997 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "D" General, undated (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "E" General, undated (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "F" General, circa 1980-circa 1983 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "G" General, circa 1983-circa 1994 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "H" General, circa 1993-circa 1998 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "K" General, circa 1994-circa 1995 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "M" General, circa 1997-circa 2009 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "N" General, circa 1988-circa 2006 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "O" General, undated (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "P" General, circa 1988-circa 1993 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "R" General, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Moderately-known correspondents, "S" General, 1991–2007 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - Well-known correspondents, "A" General, 1997–2005 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Adams, Alice, undated (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Apple, Max, undated (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Well-known correspondents, "B" General, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Well-known correspondents, "C" General, undated (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Christie, Julie, circa 1981-circa 1996 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Well-known correspondents, "D" General, circa 1997-circa 2002 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Well-known correspondents, "E" General, undated (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Well-known correspondents, "F" General, circa 1978-circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Well-known correspondents, "G" General, undated (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Well-known correspondents, "H" General, circa 1996-circa 2007 (Box 9, Folder 127)
    - Hoagland, Edward, circa 1990-circa 1999 (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Well-known correspondents, "I" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Well-known correspondents, "K" General, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Well-known correspondents, "L" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - Well-known correspondents, "M" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 132)
    - Michaels, Leonard, circa 1988-circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - Well-known correspondents, "O" General, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - Ozick, Cynthia, circa 1977-circa 2004 (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - Well-known correspondents, "P" General, circa 1996-circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Padgett, Ron, circa 1964-circa 1992 (Box 9, Folder 137)
    - Well-known correspondents, "R" General, circa 1973-circa 2002 (Box 9, Folder 138)
    - Well-known correspondents, "S" General, circa 1986-circa 2000 (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Well-known correspondents, "T" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Trilling, Diana and Lionel, circa 1966-circa 1994 (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Well-known correspondents, "U" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 142)
    - Well-known correspondents, "W" General, undated (Box 9, Folder 143)
    - Well-known correspondents, "Z" General, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Older correspondence
    While Lopate described these letters as "older," they may be more recently dated than other correspondence.
    - Amorous notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 145)
    - Amorous notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 146)
    - Letters from fans, undated (Box 10, Folder 147-151)
    - Letters from fans, undated (Box 11, Folder 152)
    - Letters from students, undated (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - Letters of condolences to Phillip Lopate upon his mother's death, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 153A)
    - Letters to Phillip Lopate from camp [from family and friends], circa 1958-circa 1959 (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - "B" General, circa 1960-circa 1977 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - "C" General, undated (Box 11, Folder 156)
    - Degener, David, undated (Box 11, Folder 157)
    - "F" General, circa 1993-circa 1996 (Box 12, Folder 158)
    - "G" General, undated (Box 12, Folder 159-160)
    - "H" General, undated (Box 12, Folder 161)
    - Hoffman, Marv and Roselle, circa 1985 (Box 12, Folder 162)
    - Hubert, Karen, undated (Box 12, Folder 163)
    - "J" General, undated (Box 12, Folder 164)
    - James, Terrell, circa 1982-circa 1983 (Box 12, Folder 165-166)
    - "K" General, circa 1999-circa 2006 (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - Kushner, Marty, undated (Box 13, Folder 168)
    - "L" General, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 169)
    - "M" General, circa 1993-circa 1996 (Box 13, Folder 170)
    - Mayer, Christine, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 171)
    - Meyers, Bill, undated (Box 13, Folder 172)
    - Minichiello, Peter, circa 1985-circa 1989 (Box 13, Folder 173)
    - Newstar, Liz, undated (Box 13, Folder 174)
    - Newstar, Liz, undated (Box 14, Folder 175)
    - "O" General, circa 1980-circa 1985 (Box 14, Folder 176)
    - "R" General, circa 1990-circa 1996 (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - Stevenson, Diane, circa 1978-circa 1980 (Box 14, Folder 178-180)
    - "W" General, undated (Box 14, Folder 181)
  - Public appearances, translations, and business correspondence
    - "A Floating Desire: An Introduction to Culture, Taste, and Fashion" correspondence with annotated drafts, undated (Box 15, Folder 182)
    - Business correspondence, undated (Box 15, Folder 183)
    - Correspondence and solicitation from magazines and newspapers, undated (Box 15, Folder 184)
    - Public appearances, general, undated (Box 15, Folder 185-187)
    - Public appearances, general, undated (Box 16, Folder 188-192)
    - Public appearances, general, undated (Box 17, Folder 193-194)
    - "The Past Recaptured" mostly rejection letters from Best Friends, undated (Box 17, Folder 195)
    - Warhol Foundation, Civitella Ranieri book and grant proposals, undated (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - Reviews, publicity, and letters for books
    - Against Joie De Vivre publicity and correspondence, undated (Box 17, Folder 197-198)
    - American Movie Critics Anthology correspondence and drafts, undated (Box 18, Folder 199)
    - The Art of the Personal Essay reviews and correspondence, undated (Box 18, Folder 200-203)
    - At the End of the Day: Selected Poems for review, undated (Box 18, Folder 204-205)
    - Bachelorhood correspondence, undated (Box 19, Folder 206)
    - Bachelorhood reviews, undated (Box 19, Folder 207)
    - Being With Children book promotion correspondence, undated (Box 19, Folder 208)
    - Being With Children letters, undated (Box 19, Folder 209)
    - Being With Children quotes, undated (Box 19, Folder 210)
    - Being With Children reviews, undated (Box 19, Folder 211)
    - Confessions of Summer correspondence, undated (Box 19, Folder 212)
    - Confessions of Summer reviews and publications, undated (Box 19, Folder 213)
    - Essay Annual reviews and publicity, undated (Box 20, Folder 214)
    - Getting Personal reviews, undated (Box 20, Folder 215)
    - Journal of a Living Experiment correspondence, undated (Box 20, Folder 216)
    - Portrait Inside My Head and To Show and to Tell publicity and correspondence, undated (Box 20, Folder 217-218)
    - Portrait of My Body reviews and correspondence, undated (Box 20, Folder 219-221)
    - Portrait of My Body reviews and publicity, undated (Box 20, Folder 222)
    - Portrait of My Body reviews and publicity, undated (Box 21, Folder 223-224)
    - Rudy Burckhardt monograph publicity and correspondence, undated (Box 21, Folder 225)
    - Totally, Tenderly, Tragically publicity and correspondence, undated (Box 21, Folder 226)
    - Two Marriages publicity and correspondence, undated (Box 21, Folder 227)
    - Writing New York clippings, undated (Box 21, Folder 228)
    - Writing New York publicity, undated (Box 21, Folder 229)
- Writings, 1963-2009 and undated; 2; 21.75 Linear Feet (44 boxes)
  This series documents Lopate's creative process and contains manuscripts, typescripts, proofs, research notes, reviews, and related materials for published and unpublished works, including essays, book reviews, literary criticism, poems, short stories, writings on film, screenplays, novels, and biographies of Rudy Burckhardt and Susan Sontag. Among the titles represented in the series are Lopate's first novel Best Friends, The Rug Merchant, Bachelorhood, the novella Two Marriages, and Spanish and Italian translations of Two Marriages. There are also manuscripts and typescripts of short stories and school papers written while Lopate was attending Columbia University. The series further contains printed versions of several works by Lopate, notably an inscribed limited-edition copy of the short story In Coyoacan (1971) and a page proof of The Anchor Essay Annual: Best of 1998. Heading and folder titles appearing in the contents list below are based on those provided by the creator.
  Organized into five subseries: Shorter works, Books, Screenplays, Early works, and Printed materials
  - Shorter works
    - Architecture, urbanism, and photography [articles and essays]
      - Ada Louise Huxtable interview, undated (Box 22, Folder 230)
      - Architecture and urbanism, general, undated (Box 22, Folder 231-232)
      - Architecture and urbanism notebook, undated (Box 22, Folder 233)
      - Big New York novel, undated (Box 22, Folder 234)
      - Brooklyn Bridge and Brooklyn pieces, undated (Box 22, Folder 235)
      - Fulton Fish Market, undated (Box 22, Folder 236-238)
      - Fulton Fish Market notebooks, undated (Box 23, Folder 239)
      - "Here Brooklyn Gathers: Merging Community and Cultural Identity" drafts, notes, emails, undated (Box 23, Folder 240)
      - Introduction emails and drafts, undated (Box 23, Folder 241)
      - Lopate's notes as a consultant for Ric Burns' history of New York City film, undated (Box 23, Folder 242)
      - "Manhattan, Floating World", undated (Box 23, Folder 243)
      - New York City breakfast club notebooks, undated (Box 23, Folder 244)
      - New York City breakfast club notes and drafts, undated (Box 23, Folder 245)
      - New York City's fiscal crisis, undated (Box 23, Folder 246-247)
      - New York City's fiscal crisis notebooks, undated (Box 23, Folder 248)
      - New York nostalgia piece, undated (Box 23, Folder 249)
      - Photography and art, undated (Box 23, Folder 250)
      - Seven Days Architecture and Urbanism column, undated (Box 23, Folder 251)
      - Small urbanism and architecture notebooks, undated (Box 24, Folder 252)
      - "Strolling up Madison Avenue", undated (Box 24, Folder 253)
      - "Thurgood Marshall Courthouse" draft, undated (Box 24, Folder 254)
      - Urbanism and architecture, general, undated (Box 24, Folder 255)
      - Urbanism and architecture, clippings, undated (Box 24, Folder 256)
    - Book reviews and literary criticism
      - General [by Lopate], undated (Box 24, Folder 257)
      - Book reviews and occasional pieces [by Lopate], undated (Box 24, Folder 258)
      - Book reviews by Phillip Lopate, undated (Box 24, Folder 259-262)
      - Book reviews by Phillip Lopate, clippings, undated (Box 24, Folder 263)
      - Book reviews by Phillip Lopate, clippings, undated (Box 25, Folder 264-268)
      - "The Days of the Patriarchs: Washington Irving's 'A History of New York'" review and drafts by Lopate, undated (Box 25, Folder 269-272)
      - "The Dean of American Essayists" Edward Hoagland piece by Phillip Lopate, emails and drafts, undated (Box 25, Folder 273)
      - Esquire advice column pieces, undated (Box 25, Folder 273A)
      - Literary Cavalcade, undated (Box 26, Folder 274-276)
      - Max Beerbohm notes, drafts, and research, undated (Box 26, Folder 277-278)
      - Ralph Waldo Emerson, undated (Box 26, Folder 279)
      - Uncollected book reviews and literary criticism, undated (Box 26, Folder 280-281)
    - Drafts of essays, stories, and poems, complete and unfinished
      - General, undated (Box 27, Folder 282-286)
      - Copies of drafts, general, undated (Box 27, Folder 287-290)
      - "Adultery and Social Chatter: 'Irretrievable' by Theodor Fontane," introduction by Phillip Lopate, undated (Box 27, Folder 291)
      - "Always be Closing: A Skeptic's View of Contemporary Short Stories" draft and clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 292)
      - Diaries project, undated (Box 28, Folder 293)
      - Earlier drafts of published pieces, undated (Box 28, Folder 294)
      - "The Empty Space" notes and drafts, undated (Box 28, Folder 295)
      - "Ghost Story" drafts and notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 296)
      - "Greenwich Village in the Summer" clippings, research, notes, drafts, undated (Box 28, Folder 297-300)